Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art records
1973-1988
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art
18 linear feet
The records of the Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art measure 18 linear feet, date from 1973 to 1988, and document the brief thirteen-year history of LAICA's activities as a Southern California visual arts organization and exhibition space for contemporary art. Records detail the founding of the organization, operations and administration, exhibitions, events, and publications. More than half of the collection is comprised of exhibition, program, and event files that include correspondence with artists, curators, and others; printed materials; and photographs, negatives, and slides.
Provenance
The bulk of the Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art records were donated by Judy Spence, the former Chair of the LAICA Board of Directors, in 1986. Additional material was donated in 1997 by her husband, Stuart Spence.
Related Material
Found in the Archives of American Art are the Peter Plagens papers, 1941-1987, which include meeting minutes and correspondence relating to LAICA.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Historical Note
The Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art was formed between 1973-1974 to provide a permanent exhibition venue for the visual contemporary arts in the Los Angeles area. The founding principle was to establish an arts organization that operated democratically and spoke with a multiplicity of voices. In order to remain flexible and minimize operating expense, LAICA did not establish a permanent collection.
Members of the Board of Directors included Peter Alexander, John Baldessari, Rosamund Felsen, Peter Plagens, Judy Spence, and other artists, gallery owners, and members of the art community. Committees that supervised exhibition programming and LAICA's published Journal were elected by members, and the duties of exhibition curator and periodical editor rotated among members, rather than being the responsibility of permanent staff. A registry of slides and biographical materials, begun in 1971, was open to submission by any Southern California artist. LAICA's first exhibitions were held in the fall of 1974, under founding director Robert Smith, a former curator at the Brand Library and Art Center in Glendale, California. The first issue of Journal was published in June of the same year.
LAICA's first exhibition space consisted of 4,200 square feet on the fifth floor of the Century City complex. During the mid-1970s, the organization hosted numerous exhibitions and events - all were were well attended, despite the lack of parking and restrooms. Exhibitions focused on a wide variety of contemporary painting, sculpture, decorative arts, fashion, performance art, video, music, architecture, social issues, and public art. Exhibitions were curated by both LAICA staff and guest curators, including Walter Hopps. Desiring to expand their space, LAICA had hopes of Frank Gehry redesigning the Century City space. The institute, however, was forced to relocate after losing their lease.
In March of 1977, LAICA reopened in an 8,000 square foot facility on 2020 South Robertson Boulevard. In addition to their public programming, the organization created an Artist-in-Residence program with funding made available by the Comprehensive Employment Training Act (CETA). By the end of the 1970s, LAICA was flourishing with increased budget and staff, and, by 1980, opened a second exhibition space at 815 Traction Avenue, referred to as the "Downtown Gallery." An additional storefront exhibition space in the Eastern Columbia building was donated by State Senator Alan Sieroty.
A decrease in public funding in the early 1980s forced LAICA to cut some of its public programs. The organization, however, still staged ambitious exhibitions, including one of contemporary Italian art that traveled to nine different venues, and a show of nine contemporary Australian artists in connection with the 1984 Olympics Art Festival.
Robert Smith resigned from his position as director in early 1985. Ben Marks, the former director of the Center of Contemporary Art in Seattle, was hired that summer. By March of 1986, however, Marks had resigned and the Board of Directors decided to sell LAICA's South Robertson location. Faced with financial burdens and the lack of a permanent exhibition space, LAICA staged exhibits at temporary spaces around Los Angeles. The Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art officially closed in 1987 after thirteen years of operation.
Scope and Content Note
The Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art records measure 18 linear feet, date from 1973 to 1988, and document the founding of the organization, board activities, general operations and administration, exhibitions, programs, events, and publications.
Founding documents and Board of Director's files contained in the collection include the articles of confederation, by-laws, constitution, director's reports, board meeting minutes, and scattered correspondence of Peter Plagens and Judy Spence, both of whom served as Chair of the Board. These records detail the mission, organization, objectives, and goals of LAICA.
More than half of the records are comprised of exhibition, program, and event files covering LAICA's entire history of operation. Included are exhibition announcements and catalogs; correspondence with artists, curators, and organizers; press releases and other publicity; grant applications and proposals; and photographs, contact sheets, negatives, and slides which depict the exhibition's installation and works of art.
Two series of photographs and slides provide additional visual documentation of LAICA's exhibitions and events, including the installations and work of LAICA's Artists-in-Residence program. Slides depicting LAICA's buildings, offices, and staff activities are also found.
LAICA's production of its publications, including material related to their regular periodical, Journal, is well-documented through correspondence, manuscripts, and editorial files. Also found are unedited transcripts of interviews and material that was not used for publication. Meeting minutes and correspondence represent the activities of the publication committee from the mid 1970s to 1987.
The correspondence of LAICA directors Robert Smith (18 folders) and Ben Marks (one folder) contain information on almost all of the organization's activities, including exhibitions, events, funding, staffing, and general operations. General Operations files include Administrative Files and Financial Files that document members and donors, staff, financial activities, fundraising efforts, income, expenses, and grants.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects-Topical:
Art, Modern -- 20th century; Art centers -- California -- Los Angeles; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- California, Southern -- Exhibitions; Painters; Photographers; Sculptors
Types of Materials:
Sound Recordings; Slides (photographs); Photographs
Names:
Smith, Robert Lewis; Marks, Ben; Plagens, Peter; Spence, Judy
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 8 series.
Slides were separated from Series 1-6, and filed in Series 8 for better preservation housing.
Series 1: Board of Directors, 1973-1987 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet )
Series 2: Correspondence, early 1970s-1987 (Boxes 1-2; 0.75 linear feet )
Series 3: General Operations, 1974-1988, undated (Boxes 2-3; 1.25 linear feet)
Series 4: Publicity, 1974-1986 (Box 3; 15 folders)
Series 5: Exhibitions and Programs, 1974-1987 (Boxes 3-13; 9.5 linear feet)
Series 6: Publications, 1974-1987 (Boxes 13-15; 2.75 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, mid-1970s-1983 (Box 15; 11 folders)
Series 8: Slides, 1974-1987 (Boxes 16-18; 3.0 linear feet)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Board of Directors, 1973-1987, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
  Found here are the records of LAICA's Board of Directors, including scattered correspondence. Members of the Board included Peter Alexander, John Baldessari, Rosamund Felsen, Peter Plagens, Judy Spence, and other artists, gallery owners, and members of the art community. Arranged within this series are founding and governing documents, such as the articles of confederation, constitution, by-laws, meeting minutes and notes, lists and biographies of board members, director's reports to the board, and prospectus. Three folders of correspondence contain letters to and from board members, primarily Peter Plagens and Judy Spence, both of whom served as Chair.
  - Articles of Confederation, 1973-1974, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographies of Board Members, early 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - By-laws, circa 1974-1975, 1979, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Constitution, circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Director's Reports, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Election Materials, circa 1979, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - List of Board Members, 1978-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1973-1974, 1977-1987, (9 folders) (Box 1, Folder 9-17)
  - Notes, late 1970s, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Proposal For Cooperation with Beyond Baroque, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Prospectus, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Prospectus, Draft, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, Undated, circa late 1970s-early 1980s (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, early 1970s-1987, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-2; 0.75 linear feet)
  LAICA Director Robert Smith's correspondence comprises the bulk of this series. Smith was director from 1974-1985, and his correspondence dates from 1979-1985. Robert Smith was followed by Ben Marks who served from 1985-1986 when LAICA folded, and one folder of his correspondence is found here. In addition, there is one file of general staff correspondence and one file of form letters. The correspondence contains information about a wide range of operating topics including exhibitions, funding, and staffing.
  The correspondence of Robert Smith has been arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Additional correspondence relating to LAICA's exhibitions, programs, and publications is found in Series 5, Exhibitions and Programs and Series 6, Publications.
  - Robert Smith, "A," 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Robert Smith, "B," 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Robert Smith, "C," 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Robert Smith, "D-E," 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Robert Smith, "F," 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Robert Smith, "G," 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Robert Smith, "H-I," 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Robert Smith, "J," 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Robert Smith, "K," 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Robert Smith, "L," 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Robert Smith, "M," 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Robert Smith, "N-O," 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Robert Smith, "P-Q," 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Robert Smith, "R," 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Robert Smith, "Sa-Sn," 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Robert Smith, "So-Sz," 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Robert Smith, "T-V," 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Robert Smith, "W-Z," 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Ben Marks, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1979-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Form Letters, early 1970s-early 1980s (Box 2, Folder 3)
- General Operations, 1974-1988, Series 3:; (Boxes 2-3; 1.25 linear feet)
  This series consists of records that document the the administrative, financial, and legal activities of LAICA. Administrative materials include files about LAICA's members and donors, lists of LAICA's staff, and information about LAICA's organizational structure. Financial records consist of financial reports, bank account information, and invoices. Legal materials include leases for LAICA's South Robertson and Traction Avenue properties, tax filings, and financial documents filed with the city of Los Angeles. This series also contains extensive documentation of LAICA's applications to receive funding from federal and state agencies.
  Additional administrative and financial records are found in Series 5, Exhibitions and Programs and Series 6, Publications.
  This series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  3.1: Administrative Files, circa 1974-1988
  3.2: Legal and Financial Records, 1974-1987, undated
  - Administrative Files, circa 1974-1988, 3.1
    Found here are records relating to the general operations and administration of LAICA. The bulk of the files relate to grant fund applications and general fundraising. Grant proposals are to the National Endowment for the Arts, Institute of Museum Services, and the Southern California Center for the Arts, and include funded projects and denied proposals. The denied grants provide information about proposed exhibits and programs that are not documented elsewhere.
    Also found in this subseries are files concerning membership and donors, staff, committees and an advisory council, space and floor plans, and works of art sold by LAICA which were possibly donated by artists for fundraising purposes. The material is arranged in a rough alphabetical order according to either topic, activity, or type of material.
    - Address Lists, mid 1970s-late 1980s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Advisory Council, 1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Advocates and Sponsors, circa 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Art Sales, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Floor Plans, circa 1974-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Forms, circa late 1970s-early 1980s (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Fundraising Materials, circa early 1980s (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Grant Applications, Institute of Museum Services, 1982-1985, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - Grant Applications, National Endowment for the Arts, 1980-1988, (13 folders) (Box 2, Folder 13-25)
    - Grant Applications, National Museum Act, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Grant Applications, Southern California Center for the Arts, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Grant Applications, Letters of Support, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Grant Applications, Other Materials 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Grant Funding List, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Job Descriptions, circa late 1970s-mid 1980s (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Membership Lists, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Member Questionnaire, circa 1983 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Museum Assessment Program, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Organizational Charts, late 1970s-mid 1980s (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Salary Survey, circa late 1970s (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Staff Lists, 1970s and circa 1985 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Legal and Financial Records, 1974-1987, 3.2
    Financial records found within this subseries include financial reports, lists of financial contributions, banking and tax documentation, and files concerning the purchase and sale LAICA's property at 2020 South Robertson Boulevard and 811 Traction Avenue. Legal records including leases, and government business filings. Also included are scattered records relating to a typesetting service ran by LAICA in the early 1980s.
    - 2020 South Robertson Building, Purchase 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - 2020 South Robertson Building, Sale1985-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
    - 811 Traction Avenue Building, 1979-1983, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 41-43)
    - Affirmative Action Materials, 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Bank Account Information, circa late 1970s (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Chart of Accounts, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Contributions, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Financial Reports, 1974-1987, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - Financial Reports, undated, circa late 1970s-mid 1980s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Invoices, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Notes, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Promissory Notes and Loans, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Taxes, 1974-1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Typesetting Materials, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Workers Compensation, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Publicity, 1974-1986, Series 4:; (Box 3; 15 folders)
  This series consists of publicity materials. Found are membership brochures, announcements and clippings about LAICA and its programs, chronologies, press lists and press releases, and other miscellenous promotional documents.
  Press releases, publicity, and clippings about specific exhibitions and programs are also found in Series 5, Exhibitions and Programs.
  - Chronologies, early 1970s-mid 1980s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1974-1982, 1984-1986, (10 folders) (Box 3, Folder 13-22)
  - Brochures and Announcements, late 1970s-mid 1980s (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Press Lists, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Press Releases, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Quotations, late 1970s (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Exhibitions and Programs, 1974-1987, Series 5:; (Boxes 3-13; 9.5 linear feet)
  Found within this series are the records documenting LAICA's exhibition and public programming. Exhibition Committee Files and Exhibition Files provide comprehensive documentation of LAICA's exhibition history, including exhibitions curated by LAICA staff and notable guest curators Walter Hopps, Llyn Foulks, and Mike Kelley. Focusing on broad and varied contemporary visual arts, the exhibitions included established and emerging artists of the Los Angeles area, the West Coast, Europe, and Asia. Contemporary Italian and Japanese artists were widely exhibited. Contemporary social and environmental issues were also covered in exhibitions, such as The James Bay Project, which documented the impact of hydroelectric stations in northwestern Quebec.
  Extensive files are found for several significant LAICA exhibitions, such as Nine Senior California Painters, 1974-1975, which featured the work of Florence Arnold, Nick Brigante, Hans Burkhardt, Annita Delano, Lorser Feitelson, Peter Krasnow, Helen Lundeberg, John McLaughlin, and Emerson Woelffer, an exhibition of Leroy Neiman and Andy Warhol, 1981-1982, Cabin, Temple, Trailer curated by Charles Moore in 1983, Il Modo Italiano, 1984 that featured the work of 10 contemporary Italian artists, and Australia: Nine Contemporary Artists, 1984. The organization provided opportunities for emerging artists as well, including a "painting of the month" exhibition series.
  Program Files document LAICA's public programming, including lecture series, workshops, and conferences. This series contains files for innovative fundraising events, such as fashion shows, film screenings, and "LAICA Sells Out", an innovative program that invited donors and artists to purchase portions of LAICA's exhibition space to display their artwork. Extensive documentation of LAICA's Artist Registry of Southern California artists and the CETA-funded Artist-in-Residence program is found here as well.
  Also found in this series are LAICA's Artist Files, comprised of printed materials, photographs, and resumes of artists, as well as scattered correspondence.
  The Exhibition and Programs series is arranged into 4 subseries:
  5.1: Exhibition Committee Files, mid 1970s-1987
  5.2: Exhibition Files, 1974-1987
  5.3: Program Files, 1975-1986
  5.4: Artist Files, circa 1980s
  - Exhibition Committee Files, mid 1970s-1987, 5.1
    Records of the Exhibitions Committee include meeting minutes, proposed exhibition schedules, policies, exhibition budgets, lists of exhibitions, and scattered correspondence. Also included is a list of LAICA's library holdings and video acquisitions.
    - Exhibition Budgets, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Committee Members, circa early 1980s (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Exhibition Schedules, 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Form Letters, late 1970s-mid 1980s (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Lists of Exhibitions and Events, 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Library Contents, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1978, 1982, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Notes, mid 1970s-mid 1980s (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Policies and Procedures, mid 1970s-1985 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Proposal Evaluations, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Video Library, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Exhibition Files, 1974-1987, 5.2
    LAICA's exhibition files are comprehensive and form the bulk of this collection. However, the extent of documentation for each exhibition varies - most are represented with one or two folders, although a few have numerous folders of documentation. Each exhibition file may contain a wide variety of materials, typically budgets; correspondence with artists, curators, and organizers; grant applications; loan agreements; and resumes. Visual documentation includes photographs, contact sheets, and negatives of artwork, installation views, and events. The file for Lecto Divina also contains audio documentation. Files also include printed materials such as press releases, clippings, announcements and invitations, and catalogs. Of special interest are questionnaires completed by ceramicists working in California which were collected for the exhibition Foundations In Clay. Files for proposed, but unrealized, exhibitions are also found here.
    Exhibition Files have been arranged chronologically by date of exhibition opening. Proposed exhibition files are filed under "P". For preservation housing, slides from the exhibition files have been removed and are now housed in Series 8, Slides. Photographs, however, have not been separated and remain within the exhibition files.
    - Syncantics, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Nine Senior California Artists, November 1974-January 1975 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Florence Arnold
      Nick Brigante
      Hans Burkhardt
      Annita Delano
      Lorser Feitelson
      Peter Krasnow
      Helen Lundeberg
      John McLaughlin
      Emerson Woelffer
    - Nina Sobel, November 1974 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - The Kipper Kids, December 1974 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Current Concerns Part One, January 1975-Febuary 1975 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      Curated by Walter Hopps
    - Current Concerns Part Two, February 1975-March 1975 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Relay, March 1975 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      Joan Jonas
    - Collage and Assemblage, April 1975-May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      Curated by Hal Glickman
    - John White and Guy de Cointet, May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Object/Subject, May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      Michael Davis
      Mary Fish
      Don Graves
      Paul Maull
      Brian Miller
      Greg Miller
      Stephen Moore
      Bradley Smith
      Richard Turner
      Bruce Williams
    - Clay Works in Progress, July 1975-August 1975 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      Tom Colgrove, George Geyer, Tom McMillin, Larry Shep, Roger Sweet
    - Three L.A. Sculptors, September 1975-October 1975, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 50-51)
      Lloyd Hamrol, George Herms, Bruce Nauman
    - Collector's Choice, November 1975-December 1975 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Autobiographical Fantasies, January 1976-Febuary 1976 (Box 3, Folder 53)
      Eleanor Antin
      Carole Caroompas
      Jennifer Griffiths
      Barry Markowitz
      Ilene Segalove
      Allan Sekula
      Alexis Smith
      John White
    - 3 For Icarus, December 1975 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Greg Calvert, Bob Covington, John Duncan, Tom Radloff, Bart Thrall, and Jim Welling, February 1976 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Exhibitions and Presentations, March 1976-April 1976 (Box 3, Folder 56)